My name is Erik Demaine. You should call me Erik.
我是Erik Demaine  叫我Erik就好
Welcome back to 6.046. This is Lecture 2.
欢迎回到6.046的课堂  这是第二讲
And today we are going to essentially fill in
今天我们要好好巩固一下
some of the more mathematical underpinnings of Lecture 1.
在第一讲提到的数学基础
So, Lecture 1, we just sort of barely got our feet
第一讲  我们稍稍涉及到了
wet with some analysis of algorithms,
一点算法分析
insertion sort and mergesort.
插入排序和归并排序
And we needed a couple of tools.
我们需要一些处理工具
We had this big idea of asymptotics
我们有了渐近的大局观
and forgetting about constants,
就是忽略常数
just looking at the lead term.
只关注打头那一项
And so, today, we're going to develop asymptotic notation
今天我们从数学的角度
so that we know that mathematically.
介绍渐近符号
And we also ended up with a recurrence with mergesort,
我们上次快结束时讲到了归并排序中的递归式
the running time of mergesort,
用已计算归并排序的运行时间
so we need to see how to solve recurrences.
这样得先知道如何求解递归式
And we will do those two things today.
今天就讲两件事
Question?
有问题吗
Yes, I will speak louder. Thanks.
行  我大声点  谢谢
Good. Even though I have a microphone, I am not amplified.
虽然带了麦克风  但是功放没开
OK, so let's start with asymptotic notation.
好的  开始讲渐近符号
We have seen some basic asymptotic notation.
有些基本的渐近符号
I am sure you have seen it in other classes before,
你肯定在其他课见过
things like big O-notation.
比如大O符号
And today we are going to really define this rigorously
今天  给它一个严格的定义
so we know what is true and what is not,
这样才能了解什么成立　什么不成立
what is valid and what is not.
以确什么合法　什么不合法
We are going to define,
我们定义
and unfortunately today is going to be really mathematical
不幸  今天讲的都是数学
and really no algorithms today,
不涉及算法
which is sort of an anticlimax.
有点扫兴
But next lecture we will talk about real algorithms
但是下一讲会完全讨论算法
and will apply all the things we learned today
并应用到今天的内容
to real algorithms.
到那些算法上
This is big O-notation,capital O-notation.
这是大O符号  大写的O
We have f(n)=O(g(n)).
这是  f(n)=O(g(n))
This means that there are some suitable constants,
表示存在适当的常数
c and n naught,
c和n₀
such that f(n) is bounded by c·g(n)
使得f(n)小于或等于c·g(n)
for all sufficiently large n.
对于充分大的n成立
So, this is pretty intuitive notion.
这个很符合直觉
We have seen it before.
以前见过
We are going to assume that f(n) is non-negative here.
这里要假设f(n)非负
And I just want f(n) to be bounded above by g(n).
我只是要使得f(n)以g(n)为上界
We have seen a bunch of examples,
有很多例子
but something like 2n^2=O(n^3) defined.
比如  2n²=O(n³)
And roughly this means if you drop leading constants
粗略的说  去掉首项系数
and low order terms then this is less than or equal to that.
和低阶项  剩下的小于或等于n³
So, big O corresponds roughly to less than or equal to.
大O粗略地说就是小于或等于
But this is the formalization.
这是其公式化定义
Another way to think of it formally,
从另外一个角度来看
a funny thing about this notation is it is asymmetric.
这个符号有意思的地方在于　它并不对称
Normally, you think of equality being symmetric.
一般来说  你会认为等号是对称的
If A=B then B=A.
如果A等于B  则B等于A
But it's not true here.
但是这里不是
We do not have n^3 being big O of n^2.
n³并非O(n²)
We don't even have big O of n^3 equaling n^2.
甚至O(n³)也并不等于n²
So, we will see exactly what that means in a second.
等下你就知道为什么了
But before we get there,
在这之前
this is a bit bizarre notation
这是个有点奇怪的符号
and you should always think about what it really means.
要时时想着它到底代表什么
Another way to think about what it really means is
另一个反映它本质的想法是
that f(n) is in some set of functions that are like g.
f(n)属于g(n)构成的函数集
You could define big O(g(n)) to be a set of functions,
可以定义O(g(n))为一个函数集
let's call it f(n),
集合内的函数记作f(n)
such that there exist constants.
对于这些函数  存在常数
They are the same definition,
同样的定义
I think, fancy here, c and no,
我觉得这个妙不可言  c和n₀
such that we have the bound f(n) is between zero and c·g(n).
使得f(n)以0和c·g(n)为界
It is a bit of a long definition,
很长的定义
and that is why we use the notation,
这也是为什么要使用符号
to avoid having to write this over and over.
这样不用反复写这定义
You can think of instead of n^2
不能把它理解为
being equal to big O of n^3,
n²等于O(n³)
what we really mean is that 2n^2 is in the set big O(n^3).
而只能理解为2n²属于函数集O(n³)
When we write equal sign,
我们写的是等于号
we in some sense mean this in the set,
但表达的意思是属于某个集合
but we are going to use equal sign.
但我们还是照样写等于号
You could write this.
这么写没问题
And occasionally you see papers that write this,
偶尔能看到些论文这样写
but this is the notation that we are going to use.
但是我们以后还是用这个符号
That has the consequence the equal sign is asymmetric,
由上可知  这个等号是不对称的
just like this operator.
就像这个属于集合符号
We have some nifty ways
我们还有一些大O符号的
that we actually use big O-notation.
精妙用法
And it is using it as a macro.
这里  把它当做宏来用
By the way, we have a lot to cover today,
顺便说下  今天内容很多
so I am going to go relatively fast.
我相对要讲的快点
If anything is unclear,
如果哪儿不明白
just stop, ask questions,then I will slow down.
向我提问  我就停下来细说
Otherwise, I will take this as all completely obvious
否则  我假设大家都明白了
and I can keep going at full speed.
然后全速前进
The convention, this is intuitive,
宏的用法很直观
I guess, if you do some macro programming or something,
如果你写过带宏的程序的话
but it's a bit more mathematical.
但这里多点数学
We have defined big O-notation
我们定义了大O符号
and it equals big O of something.
某个函数等于某个大O符号
And so we have only defined big O
但我们只定义了某个函数等于
when on the equal sign we have big O of some function.
某个大O符号的用法
But it is useful to have some general expression
但是如果有某些置于更一般的表达式右侧的
on the right-hand side that involves big O.
大O符号　就会更有用处
For example, let's say we have f(n) = n^3 +O(n^2).
比如  f(n)=n³+O(n²)
This is attempting to get an error bound.
这里表示了一个误差界限
This is saying f(n) is basically n^3
意思是 f(n)主要是n³
but there are these lower order terms that are O(n^2).
但是还有一些低阶项O(n²)
And so this means that there is a function,
具体来说 即存在某函数
shorthand for a function, h(n) which is in O(n^2)
h(n)在函数集O(n²)中
or equals O(n^2) such that f(n)=n^3 + h(n).
使得f(n)=n³+h(n)
It is saying that there are some lower order terms
总的来说  有低阶项
that are bounded above by some constant times n^2
以某个常数乘以n²为上界
for sufficiently large n,
对于足够大的n成立
and that is what is here.
就是这个
And then f(n) equals, now this is a true equality,
现在f(n)等于  现在是真正的等于
n^3 plus that error term.
n³加上那个误差项
This is very useful here.
这很有用
Essentially, I am expressing what the lead constant is
重点在于描述首项是什么
and then saying well,
然后说
there is other stuff and it's all at most n^2.
再加上至多为n²阶的项
Saying that f(n) therefore is also order n^3,
可以说f(n)因此是三阶的
but that is a bit weaker of a statement.
但这么说比较含糊
This is a bit more refined.
加上代表低阶项的大O符号更完善
We won't need to use this too often, but it is useful.
这种表达式不会用的太多  但是用处很大
Sometimes we will see,
有时我们看到
like in last class we even had a big O inside a summation.
像上讲课  大O符号出现在求和计算里
So, you can use them all over the place.
很多地方都可以用
The point is they represent some function in that set.
符号代表其所在集合中的某个函数
A bit less intuitive, and this is more subtle,
接下来的不太直观  更微妙一点
is what it means to have big O on the left-hand side.
如果大O符号出现在等号左边代表什么
It means the same thing,
和之前一样
but there is some convention what equality means.
但是等号不代表同一个意思
And this is why equal sign is asymmetric.
这是为什么此处等号不对称
You should read equals like "Is".
不是相等  而是"是"
Is means that everything over here is something over here.
"是"表示所有左边的就是右边的
So, there is an implicit for all on the left-hand side
在这里等号左边隐含了一个任意量词
and there exists on the right-hand side.
等号的右边隐含了一个存在量词
This is a true statement.
这个等式是正确的
Anything that is n^2 + O(n) is also O(n^2),
任何n²+O(n)都是O(n²)
but not the other way around.
反之则不然
So, this is a bit asymmetric.
所以不对称
If you think about it, this is pretty intuitive
想想其实挺直观的
but it is subtle so you should be careful.
但是很微妙  所以要小心
This says for any expansion of the macro on the left-hand side,
对于任何在左边宏展开的表示式
which should be f(n),
假设是f(n)
there is an expansion of the macro
都能在右边找到一个
on the right-hand side such that we get equality.
对应的展开  使得左右相等
And what this allows you to do is
有了这个概念
if you have a chain of equal signs relations,
如果你有一个等式关系链
a chain of "Is"S,
通过"某是某"组成的链式表达式
then the very first one is equal to
第一个就等于最后一个
or bounded by the very last one.
或者以最后一个为上界
So, you can chain equal signs the way you normally would.
等式可以通过链从前往后传递下去
You just cannot flip them around. Good.
但是不能反过来  从后往前
So, that's big O-notation. Any questions about that?
以上就是大O符号  有问题吗
So, big O is great for expressing upper bounds.
大O符号很好的表示了上界
But we also want to talk about lower bounds.
但是我们还需要下界
For algorithms, we usually care
对于算法  通常考虑
about upper bounds on their running time.
的是运行时间的上界
Running times at most n^2 is at most n log n up to big O,
运行时间最多是n²或nlgn
but sometimes we need to express functions
但有时需要表示函数
that are at least some quantity.
的最小值
For example, we will show that sorting requires
举例来说  之后会看到排序算法
at least n log n time in some model.
在一些模型中至少要nlgn的时间
So, we need some other notation for that.
需要其他的符号
And the notation is big Omega-notation.
就是大Ω符号
And it is pretty symmetric.
和之前的挺相似
I will just write out the set definition here.
我就只写集合版定义了
And we are going to write f(n)=big Omega g(n) to mean
f(n)等于Ω(g(n))意思是
f(n) is at least some constant times g(n) --
f(n)大于等于某个常数乘以g(n)
for sufficiently large n
对于足够大的n成立
So, I am basically just reversing the inequality relation
我只是颠倒了f和g的不等关系
between f and g, nothing surprising,
没什么特别的
just to have it there.
就写在这儿
A random example,
随便举个例子
and now we will get a little bit more sophisticated,
来个复杂点的
root n= big Omega log(n).
n的平方根等于Ω(lgn)
And you should read this that up to constant factors root n
你应该这样理解  对于充分大的n
is at least log n for sufficiently large n.
根号n至少是lgn的常数倍
So, omega sort of corresponds to greater than or equal to.
所以  Ω基本上对应大于或者等于
Let me give you some analogies.
给你一些类比
We have big O, we have big omega,
我们有大O  大Ω
this is less than or equal to,
这是小于等于
this is greater than or equal to.
这是大于等于
And I am going to fill in some more here in a moment.
等会儿还有一些
It's nice to have all the usual operators we have.
通常的符号这里都有
Normally we have strict less than,
通常的符号有小于
strict greater than and equal sign.
大于还有等于
And we want those sort of analogs in the asymptotic world
我们希望在渐近世界里也有类似符号
where we ignore constant factors
只是忽略了系数
and ignore lower order terms.
和低阶项
We have, for example, big Theta.
比如  有大Θ
This is a capital theta
大写的Θ
which means you write the horizontal bar in the middle
所以在横线应该画在中间
as opposed to all the way through.
但别挨着圆圈
I didn't invent Greek, so that is the way it is.
希腊文可不是我发明的  它就是写成那个熊样
Theta means that you are less than or equal to
Θ表示小于等于
and you are greater than or equal to
并且大于等于
up to constant factors,
对于特定常数
so it is the inner section of these two sets,
因此它是这两个集合的交集
big O and big Omega.
O和Ω
That is sort of like equal sign
因此它有点类似于等于号
but, of course,this is very different.
但显然它和等于号是不同的
You have things like n^2 is big Theta of 2
你可以看到n²=Θ(n²)
because you ignore constant factors,
因为你忽略了前面的常数系数
but all of these other relations,
但是其他所有的关系
OK, n^2 + O = Theta,
好  n²+O(n)=Θ(n²)
but this does not hold with theta
但是这里对于Θ不成立
because square root of n is really
因为n的平方根
asymptotically bigger than log n.
的确渐进地大于lgn
And some of the other examples
此外对于其他的例子
we saw like n^2 versus n^3, those don't hold with T.
我们看到n²跟n³相比  它们对于Θ是不成立的
And we have some strict notation
我们介绍一下一些严格符号
which are the little o-notation and little omega-notation.
它们是o和ω
There is no little theta because there is not notion
没有相应的小Θ因为没有
of strict equality versus unstrict equality.
相对应的严格等号和不严格等号
Little o is going to correspond roughly to less than
o大致相当于小于
and little omega is going to correspond to greater than.
而ω大致相当于大于
This is a notation you will just have to get used to.
这个符号你们以后会常常用
And I am not going to define it precisely here
我这里就不给出精确定义了
because it is almost exactly the same.
因为它们的含义几乎一样
The difference is that instead of saying
区别在于
there exists constant c and n_o,
并不是“存在”某个常数c和n₀
you have to say for every constant c
而是你们应该说对于“任意”常数c
there exists a constant n_o.
都存在一个常数 n₀
The relationship between f and g,
函数f和g之间的关系
this inequality must hold for all c instead of just for 1.
不等式要对所有的c成立
And so n_o can now depend on c.
因此现在的n₀依赖于c
You can assume that really n is sufficiently large,
你可以假设n可以足够大
but this gives you a strict inequality.
但这个是严格的不等于
No matter what constant you put here, in front of g,
不管在函数g前设置多大的常数系数
let's say we are doing little o,
我们说的是小o
f will be still less than
当n足够大时 f仍然小于
c times g for sufficiently large n.
c乘以g
We have some random examples.
我们随便举一些例子
We are again ignoring constants.
我们依然忽略常数系数
n^2 is always less than n^3 for sufficiently large n.
n足够大时n²总是小于n³
And it is a bit subtle here.
这里有些微妙之处
I mean in order to prove something like this,
为了证明类似这样的公式
it will become intuitive after you manipulate it a little bit.
在你掌握这样一些后 它就会变成你直觉的一部分
You have to figure out what n_o is in terms of c.
你得找出用c表示的n₀表达式
I think it something like 2/c.
我认为应该是2/c
If we have less than or equal to, that should be right.
如果是小于或者等于 那应该是这样
As long n is at least this big,
只要n至少这么大
no matter how small of a c,
不管c有多小
you should think of c here as being epsilon now,
这里你可以将c当作ε
in the usual epsilon and deltas.
在常规的ε-δ语言中
No matter how small c gets,
不管c能达到多小
still I can bound n^2 in terms of n^3, upper bound,
我仍然能够用n³将n²的上界加以限定
but whenever you have theta
但是当在Θ情况时
you do not have either of these relations.
将不会有上面的这些关系
For example, n^2 = Theta(n^2) and it is not little o
比如 n²/2=Θ(n²) 但它不是小o
and it not little omega because it is exactly n^2.
同时也不是ω 因为它是严格的n²
You will get some sense in order relation out of this,
从这些例子上你会得到一些直观感觉
although there are some messy behaviors
虽然他们的呈现出来的行为比较杂乱
as you will see in your problem set.
正如你在习题集里看到的那样
Any questions about asymptotic notation?
有关于渐进关系的问题吗
That is the quick rundown.
这个知识我们就这样快速地扫一下
Now we are going to use it to solve some recurrences.
现在我们将要用这个来解一些递归
Although we won't use it that much today,
虽然今天我们用得不多
we will use it a lot more on Wednesday.
星期三我们将大量应用
OK.
好
We will move onto the second topic of today,
我们进入今天的第二个主题
which is solving recurrences.
就是 解递归式
You have probably solved some recurrences
你们可能已经会解一些递归
before in 6.042 or whatever discrete math class you have taken.
在6.042里或者在离散数学课里你们掌握的
We are going to do more and have some techniques here
我们今天将做更多这样的工作并且有更多的方法
that are particularly useful for analyzing recursive algorithms,
这对于分析递归算法尤其有用
and we will see that mostly on Wednesday.
递归算法放在星期三讲
There are three main methods
这里我们主要有三种主要方法
that we are going to use here for solving recurrences.
来解递归式
The first one is the substitution method.
第一个是代换法
There is no general procedure for solving a recurrence.
迄今还没有一个通用的方法来解递归问题
There is no good algorithm for solving recurrences,unfortunately.
不幸的是没有一个好的算法来解递归问题
We just have a bunch of techniques.
我们仅仅有一堆方法
Some of them work some of the time,
有的时候这些方法有用
and if you are lucky yours will work for your recurrence,
如果幸运你自己的方法可以解你遇到的递归
but it is sort of like solving an integral.
这就有点类似于做积分
You have to just know some of them,
积分也没有通用的方法
you have to know various methods for solving them.
你必须学习各种各样的方法才能做出积分
It is usually easy to check if you have the right answer.
但是一般来说　检查是否得到正确答案是容易的
Just like with integrals,
就像积分题目那样
you just differentiate and say oh, I got the right answer.
你仅仅需要求微分  然后说　嗨　我做出来了
And that is essentially the idea of substitution method.
这个是代换法的主要思想
Substitution method will always work,
代换法大多数情况下是有效的
but unfortunately Step 1 is guess the answer.
但是不幸的是第一步是猜答案
And you have to guess it correctly.
你必须猜对它
That makes it a big difficult.
这造成了很大的困难
You don't have to guess it completely.
你不需要完全猜出来
You can usually get away with not knowing the constant factors,
你可以不需要知道常数系数确切是多少
which is a good thing because we don't
这很不错　因为我们
really care about the constant factors.
并不十分在意常数系数
You guess the form.You say oh, it is going to be roughly n^2,
你仅需要猜它的形式 你可以猜大概是n²
and so it's some constant times n^2 presumably.
因此它是n²乘上一个常数系数
So, you guess that.
你这么猜
We are going to figure out the constants.
然后我们再试图解出它的常数
You try to verify whether the recurrence
你试着去验证是否这个递归式
satisfies this bound by induction,
按照数学归纳法满足条件
and that is the key.
而这个是问题关键
Substitution uses induction.
代换法使用归纳
And from that you usually get the constants for free.
然后从那里可以容易地获得常数系数
You figure out what the constants
你设法找出什么系数
have to be in order to make this work.
可以使问题成立
So, that is the general idea.
好的 这是主要思想
You will see a few examples of this.
先看一些例子
Actually, the same example several times.
正确地说 一样的例子使用多次
Unfortunately,this is what you might call, I don't know.
不幸的是 你们可以说这是
This is an algorithm,
这是一个算法
but it uses an oracle which is knowing the right answer.
但我们需要预知正确答案
But sometimes it is not too hard to guess the answer.
但是有时并不是很难猜对答案
It depends.
这要看情况
If you look at this recurrence, T = 4T(n/2) + n,
请看这个递归式T=4T(n/2)+n
we should implicitly always have some base case
这里总是需要含有一些基本情况
of T of some constant, usually 1 is a constant,
T前面某项 通常是第一项 它是一个常数
so we don't really care about the base case.
我不是非常在意这些基本情况
For algorithms that is always the case.
对于算法来说通常都是这样的
And we want to solve this thing.
我们想解这个问题
Does anyone have a guess to what the solution is?
有人能猜一个答案吗
Ideally someone who doesn't already know
一般还是有些人不知道
how to solve this recurrence.
怎么解这个递归式
OK. How many people know how to solve this recurrence?
好的 有多少人知道怎么解这个递归式
A few, OK.
有一些 好的
And, of the rest, any guesses?
其他人呢 谁猜出来了
If you look at what is going on here,
如果你们看这个公式的形态
here you have T(n/2) and let's ignore this term more or less.
这里你有T(n/2)项 我们先忽略这一项
We have n/2 here. If we double n and get T(n)
这里是n/2  当加倍得到T(n)时
then we multiply the value by 4.
我们得到了乘数4
And then there is this additive end,
然后是这个加法余项
but that doesn't matter so much.
但是这一项不是很重要
What function do you know that when you double the argument
你知道哪一个函数在你对参数加倍时
the output goes up by a factor of 4?
输出增加到4倍
Sorry? n^2,yeah.
不好意思  n² 对的
You should think n^2 and you would be right.
如果你认为是n²那么你是对的
But we won't prove n^2 yet.
但我们现在还没有证明是n²
Let's prove something simpler,
我们先证明一些更简单的
because it turns out proving that
因为想要直接证明
it is at most n^2 is a bit of a pain.
最多是n² 是很困难的
We will see that in just a few minutes.
接下来的几分钟里我们将会看到这些
But let's guess that T = O(n³) first
我们先猜想T=O(n³)
because that will be easier to prove by induction.
因为这个更易通过归纳法来证明
You sort of see how it is done in the easy case,
你们有多少人能看出在基本情况下怎么做
and then we will actually get the right answer, n^2, later.
然后　我们可以得到正确的答案 n²
I need to prove. What I am going to do is guess that
我需要去证明 我所做的是去猜出
T is some constant times n^3 at most,
T至多n³乘以一个常数
so I will be a little more precise.
我会更精确一点
I cannot use the big O-notation in the substitution method
在代换法中我不能用O符号
so I have to expand it out to use constants.
因此我需要用常数来展开它
I will show you why in a little bit,
我给你们展示一下为什么
but let me just tell you at a high level what is important
让我在较高层次上告诉你们
in not using big O-notation.
没有使用O符号的关键之处在哪里
Big O-notation is great
大O符号很棒
if you have a finite chain of big O relations, you know,
如果你有一个有穷的大O关系序列 比如
n^2 is big O(n³) is big O(n^4) is big O(n^4) is big O(n^4).
n²　是O(n³)的　是O(n⁴)的　是O(n⁴)的　是O(n⁴)的
That is all true. And so you get that n^2 is big O.
这些都是对的 因此你得到n²是O(n⁴)
But if you have an infinite chain of those relations
但是如果你有一个无穷的大O关系序列
then the first thing is not big O of the last thing.
那么第一项和最后一项的大O关系就不成立了
You have to be very careful.
你需要很小心仔细
For example, this is a total aside on the lecture notes.
举个例子 这个完全超出了讲义的范围
Suppose you want to prove that n = O(1).
假设你想证明n=O(1)
This is a great relation.
这是个很重要的关系
If it were true, every algorithm would have constant running time
如果这个是真的 那任何算法将是常数复杂度
This is not true.
显然这是假的
Not in Wayne's World notation.
在这些符号里是假的
You could "Prove this by induction"
你可以通过归纳假设来证明这个
By saying well, base case is 1 = O(1).
从完备性上 基本情况是1=O(1)
OK, that is true.
这个是真的
And then the induction step as well,
然后是归纳步骤
if I know that n-1, so let's suppose that n-1 =O(1),
如果我知道假设n-1=O(1)
well, that implies that n, which is +1,
那可以推出n=(n-1)+1
if this is O(1) and 1 = O(1), the whole thing is O.
如果这个是O(1)并且 1=O(1) 所以总的是O(1)
And that is true.
因此是真的
If you knew that = O and 1 = O then their sum is also O,
如果你知道n-1=O(1)和1=O(1)然后它们的和是O(1)
but this is a false proof.
但是这个是错误的证明
You cannot induct over big Os.
你不能在这些大O的符号上进行归纳
What is going on here is that the constants
这里出现的问题是这些常数
that are implicit in here are changing.
它们其实是变化的
Here you have some big O of 1,
这里你有一些O(1)
You are probably doubling the constant in there
你可能对这些常数加倍
every time you do this relation.
你每次做这些东西的时候
If you have a finite number of doubling of constants,
如果你是有穷数量的常数加倍
no big deal, it is just a constant,
没大问题 它仍然是常数
two the power number of doublings.
二的某个数幂次加倍
But here you are doing n doublings and that is no good.
但是当你进行n次加倍的时候就不对了
The constant is now depending on n.
现在　该是常数依赖于n变化的
So, we are avoiding this kind of problem
因此我们需要避免这类问题
by writing out the constant.
一旦我们写出常数
We have to make sure that constant doesn't change.
我们需要保证这些常数不会变化
Good.
好
Now I have written out the constant.
现在我已经写出了常数
I should be safe.
现在应该保险了
I am assuming it for all k less than n,
我假设对于所有小于n的k
now I have to prove it for k equal to n.
现在我得证明对于k等于n的情况
I am going to take T and just expand it.
我要把T(n)拿出来展开
I am going to do the obvious thing.
我下面要做的很明显
I have this recurrence how to expand T.
我可以根据这个递归算式展开T(n)
Then it involves T.
而这有涉及到T(n/2)
And I know some fact about T
我又知道一些T(n/2)的条件
because n/2 is less than n.
因为n/2小于n
So, let's expand. T = 4T + n.
于是我们一起把T(n)展开 T(n)=4T(n/2)+n
And now I have an upper bound on this thing
现在我根据之前的归纳假设
from the induction hypothesis.
知道这部分的值域上界
This is at most 4 times c times the argument cubed plus n.
这就是T(n/2)小于等于4c(n/2)³加n
I have a feeling that by the end of the lecture
我想 等我课上完了
These blackboards will be totally stucked
这黑板也就彻底卡住了
Oh, it's not going up. Ok.
推不上去了  好了
It's ok. I will use half of the board.
行了  我就用半块黑板好了
I'd like to say it's from my super human strenth.
我倒希望是我的神力弄坏的
But I believe it's from the quality of the blackboards,
不过我确信是黑板的质量问题
or their hinges.
或者是滑轨的问题
Continuing on here. Let's expand this a little bit.
我们接上面继续展开
We have n cubed over 2 cubed.
2的三次方分之n的三次方
Two cubed is 8,so 4 over 8 is a half.
2的三次幂是8  4除以8是1/2
So, we have a half times C times n cube + n
也就是1/2·c·n³+n
And what I would like this to be is,
我想要把它化简成为
so at the bottom where I would like to go
最终的理想形式是
is that this is at most cn3.
小于等于c·n³
That is what I would like to prove to reestablish
这就是我想证明的
the induction hypothesis for n.
能把它还原成为对n的归纳假设
What I will do,in order to see when that is case,
为了确定此结果成立的条件
is just write this as what I want,
我先直接把理想的结果写上
so this is sort of the desired value,cn3,
这是我想要的理想结果  c·n³
minus whatever I don't want.
减去我想化简掉的部分
This is called the residual.
这部分是余项
Now I have to actually figure this out.
现在我得想办法凑出这个余项
Let's see. We have cn^3, but only a half n^3 here,
大家看  这里是c·n³但上面只有1/2cn³
so I need to subtract off 1/2n^3 to get that lead term correct.
所以我这里要减去一个1/2cn³让第一项正确
And then I have plus n and there is a minus here,
上面是加n  加上括号
so it is minus n.
就变成减n
And that is the residual.
这就是余项
In order for this to be at most this,
为了让cn³成为最大值
I need that the residual s non-negative.
我需要保证余项是非负的
This is if the residual part is greater than or equal to zero,
所以条件是  余项大于等于零
which is pretty easy to do because here I have control over c.
这点很容易保证  因为我可以设定c的取值
I get to pick c to be whatever I want.
我可以赋予c任何我想要的数值
And, as long as c is at least, oh, I don't know, 2,
而且只要不小于  我想想  2的话
then this is a 1 at least.
那这部分最小就是1
Then I have n^3 should be greater than or equal to n.
我就得到了n³大于等于n
And that is always the case.
此不等式永远成立
So this is, for example, this is true if c is at least 1,
比如  当c大于等于1时不等式成立
and I don't think it matters what n is
n取多少应该关系不大
but let's say n is at least 1 just for kicks.
不过我们还是写上n大于等于1
So, what we have done is proved
那么  我们就证明了
that T is at most some constant times n^3.
T(n)小于等于一个常数乘以n³
And the constant is like 1.
诸如1之类的常量
So, that is an upper bound. It is not a tight upper bound.
这就是上界   不过不是个严格的上界
We actually believed that it is n^2, and it is,
事实上我们认为n的平方也成立
but you have to be a little careful.
但是大家要注意一下
This does not mean that the answer is n^3.
这并不是指答案就是n³
It just means that at most is O(n^3).
这只是表示至多是O(n³)
And this is a proof by induction.
这就是用归纳法的证明过程
Now, technically I should have put a base case in this induction,
严格来讲  我该取一个基本值代入递归
so there is a little bit missing.
这一部分我没写
The base case is pretty easy because T(1) is some constant,
基本情况代入很简单  因为T(1)是常数
but it will sort of influence things.
但还是可能有影响
If the base case T is some constant.
如果基本值T(1)是一常数
And what we need is that it is at most c times one cubed,
我们要得到的就是≤c·1³
which is c.
也就是c
And that will be true as long as
此不等式永远成立
you choose c to be sufficiently large.
条件是c的值足够大
So, this is true if c is chosen sufficiently large.
当c的值足够大时成立
Now, we don't care about constants,
我们一般不用考虑常量的值
but the point is just to be a little bit careful.
但是在这里要注意下
It is not true that T is at most 1 times n^2,
T(n)小于等于1·n²是不成立的
even though here all we need is that c is at least 1.
尽管这里我们只需让c大于等于1
For the base case to work,
为了让基本值代入成立
c actually might have to be a hundred or whatever T is.
c的值可能要取到100  起码要等于T(1)
So, be a little bit careful there.
所以这里要注意下
It doesn't really affect the answer, usually it won't
不太会影响结果  一般不会
because we have very simple base cases here.
因为我们的基本值代入很简单
OK, so let's try to prove the tight bound of O(n^2).
好的  我们一起来证明紧界O(n²)
I am not going to prove an omega bound,
Ω界限我就不证明了
but you can prove an omega n squared bound
但你可以用代入法
as well using substitution method.
证明Ω(n²)
I will just be satisfied for now
这节课我只想证明
proving an upper bound of n squared.
上界n²
Let's try to prove that T,this is the same recurrence,
求证T(n)  与之前一样的递归式
I want to prove that it is O.
我想证明它是O(n²)
I am going to do the same thing.
按照相同的证明步骤
And I will write a bit faster because this is basically copying.
我就写快一点  因为都是原样照抄
Except now, instead of three, I have two.
这里注意  不是立方了  是平方
Then I have T = 4T + n. I expand this T(n/2).
T(n)=4T(n/2)+n  我把T(n/2)展开
This is at most 4c(n/2)^2 + n.
代入后就是小于等于4c(n/2)²+n.
And now, instead of have 2 cubed,
之前算的是2的立方
I have 2 squared, which is only 4.
而现在是2的平方  就是4
The fours cancel. I get cn^2 + n.
4就消掉了  得到cn²+n
And if you prefer to write it as desired minus residual,
然后把它写成理想结果减去余项的形式
then I have cn^2 - n.
我就得到cn²-(-n)
And I want this to be non-negative.
我需要让-n非负
And it is damn hard for minus n to be non-negative.
要让-n成为非负的　相当难
If n is zero we are happy,
如果是0的话就好了
but unfortunately this is an induction on n.
很不幸这是n的递推式
It's got to hold for all n greater than or equal to 1.
所以所有n的取值都要大于等于1
This is not less than or equal to cn^2.
所以这里不能是小于等于cn²
Notice the temptation is to write that this equals O,
注意我们的目的是让它等于O(n²)
which is true for this one step.
对于这一步来说是成立的
cn^2 -(-n) , well, these are both order n,
cn²-(-n)  n是O(n)
or this is order n, this is order n squared.
这个为O(n)  而这个为O(n²)
Certainly this thing is O(n^2), that is true,
当然相减同样为O(n²)
but it is not completing the induction.
但这是不能表示归纳完成
To complete the induction, you have to prove
为了完成归纳  你必须证明
the induction hypothesis for n with this constant c.
n时含常数c的归纳假设
Here you are getting a constant c of like c + 1,
但这里得到的常量却是c+1之类的
which is not good.
并不理想
This is true but useless.
归纳到这一步虽正确但没有用
It does not finish the induction,
无法完成归纳
so you can sort of ignore that.
所以这个就不用看了
This proof doesn't work,
这个证明不成立
which is kind of annoying because we feel,
这很难以接受  因为我们
in our heart of hearts, that T = n^2.
有预感T(n)=n²
It turns out to fix this you need to express T
为了能使证明成立  我们要将T(n)
in a slightly different form.
用一种不同的形式表达出来
This is, again, divine inspiration.
这是上帝给你们的启示
And, if you have a good connection to some divinity,
如果你们能和神扯上点关系的话
you are all set.
一切就能迎刃而解了
But it is a little bit harder for the rest of us mere mortals.
不过对于在座的诸位凡人来说就有点难了
It turns out,and maybe you could guess this,
我们可以试试这个作为猜想
that the idea is we want to strengthen the induction hypothesis.
我们的思路是改进归纳假设
We assumed this relatively weak thing,
我们之前用的这个相对弱的假设
T is less than or equal to some constant times k^2.
T(n)小于等于一个常数乘以k的平方
We didn't know what the constant was, that is fine,
我们不知道常量的取值  这倒无妨
but we assumed that there were no lower order terms.
但是我们还假设了它没有低阶项
I want to look at lower order terms.
现在我就要考虑低阶项了
Maybe they play a role.
没准这能帮上忙
And if you look at this progression you say,
如果你观察下这个计算的过程
oh, well, I am getting something like n^2
你会这些n²的项
and the constants are pretty damn tight.
其常数真是消得太他丫的巧了
I mean the fours are canceling and the c just is preserved.
4被约掉了只留下c 没一点多的
How am I going to get rid of this lower order term plus n?
我怎么才能去掉低阶项+n呢
Well, maybe I could subtract off a linear term in here and,
我也许可以从这个里面分出一个线性项来
if I am lucky,it will cancel with this one.
如果幸运的话  它就能与低阶项抵消
That is all the intuition we have at this point.
这就是我们处理这个地方的思路
It turns out it works.
结果证明可行
We look at T and this is 4T + n as usual.
这还是T(n)=4T(n/2)+n
Now we expand a slightly messier form.
现在我们用稍微复杂的形式展开
We have 4 + n.
4[c₁·(n/2)²-c₂(n/2)]+n
This part is the same because the fours cancel again.
这一项还是一样的  4被消掉
So, we get c_1*n^2, which is good.
得到c₁·n²  这很理想
I mean that is sort of the form we want.
因为这是我们想要的形式
Then we have something times n, so let's figure it out.
下一项是常数与n相乘  我们来看一下
We have a plus 1 times n,
提取n 剩下+1
so let's write it 1 minus c_2 over 2 times n.
这项是(1-c₂/2)n
Oops, got that wrong.
不对
There is four times a two so, in fact, the two is upstairs.
没把4乘进来  所以2应该到分子上去
Let me double check. Right.
在检查下  正确
OK. Now we can write this as desired minus residual.
好  现在我们可以写出想要的结果和余项
And we have to be a little careful here
不过我们要注意一下
because now we have a stronger induction hypothesis to prove.
因为我们用了更强的归纳假设来证明
We don't just need it is at most c_1*n^2,
不仅仅需要化简到只留下c₁·n²
which would be fine here
还需要保留其他项
because we could choose c_2 to be large,
因为c₂可能是一个很大的值
but what we really need is c_1*n^2 - c_2*n,
我们需要的形式是c₁·n²-c₂·n
and then minus some other stuff.
后面还要减去别的项
This is, again,desired minus residual.
这样  这里就又是理想结果减去余项
And minus residual,let's see,
我们来写出要减去的余项
That doesn't look so happy.
看着不太对
Plus c_2, thank you,
加上c₂  谢谢
because that again looked awfully negative.
差点又弄得都是负号了
It is plus c_2. I am getting my signs,
改为加上c₂  我就得到了我想要的符号
there is a minus here and there is one minus here,so there we go.
这里一个负号  这还一个  所以得正
Again, I want my residual to be greater than or equal to zero.
同样  我需要我的余项非负
And if I have that
如果我能成功
I will be all set in making this inductive argument.
我归纳的结论就得证了
Office hours start this week,
本周开始有答疑时间
in case you are eager to go.
你们有问题就可以去问
They are all held in some room in Building 24,
答疑都被安排在24号楼
which is roughly the midpoint between here and Stata,
大概就是在这里与史塔塔中心的中点
I think, for no particular reason.
我就是随便一说
And you can look at the Web page for details on the office hours.
答疑时间详情请参见网页
Continuing along,
我们继续
when is c_2 - 1 going to be greater than or equal to zero?
何时c₂-1能大于等于0
Well, that is true if c_2 is at least 1,
当c₂大于等于1时成立
which is no big deal.
这个问题不大
Again, we get to choose the constants however we want.
还是让常数等于我们想要的值
It only has to hold for some choice of constants.
只需对特定常数成立
So, we can set c_2 greater than or equal to 1.
我们可以让c₂大于等于1
And then we are happy.
这样就搞定了
That means this whole thing is
上一步写下来就是
less than or equal to c_1*n^2 - c_2*n
小于等于c₁·n²-c₂·n
if c_2 is greater than or equal to 1.
如果c₂大于等于1
It is kind of funny here.
这里就有意思了
This finishes the induction, at least the induction step.
归纳就完成了  起码完成了归纳步骤
We proved now that for any value of c_1,
我们证明了  对任意c₁
and provided c_2 is at least one.
且c₂大于等于1成立
We have to be a little more careful that c_1
我们要特别注意下 c₁
does actually have to be sufficiently large.
必须足够大
Any particular reason why?
有人知道原因吗
c_1 better not be negative, indeed.
c₁须是非负的  没错
c_1 has to be positive for this to work,
c₁是正数 递归才能成立
but it even has to be larger than positive depending.
也许它还不仅仅需要是正数
Sorry.I have been going so fast,
对不起我讲得有点快
I haven't asked you questions.
我没有提问
Now you are caught off guard. Yeah?
你们快睡着了，是不是
Because of the base case, exactly.
因为基本情况 正确
So, the base case will have T is c_1 time 1 squared minus c_2,
基本情况是c₁·1²-c₂
we want to prove that it is at most this,
我们需要证明这是上界
and T is some constant we have assumed.
假设T(1)是常数
We need to choose c_1 to be
我们需要选择c₁
sufficiently larger than c_2, in fact,
比c₂大
so c_2 has to be at least 1.
而c₂至少是1
c_1 may have to be at least a hundred more than one
c₁也许比1大100
if this is one hundred.
如果这个是100的话
so this will be true, if c_1 is sufficiently large.
若c₁足够大  则算式成立
And sufficiently large now means with respect to c_2.
足够大是相对于c₂来讲的
You have to be a little bit careful,
你需要注意这一点
but in this case it doesn't matter.
但在这个例子中无关紧要
Any questions about the substitution method?
对这个代换法有什么问题吗
That was the same example three times.
同一个例子我用了三次
In the end, it turned out we got the right answer.
最后  我们得到了正确答案
But we sort of had to know the answer in order to find it,
但我们求解时需要预先知道解
which is a bit of a pain.
这有点蛋疼
It would certainly be nicer to just
大家肯定希望
figure out the answer by some procedure,
有什么方法能直接求出答案的
and that will be the next two techniques we talk about.
这是我们将要讲的下两种方法
Sorry? How would you prove a lower bound?
如何确定下界呢
I haven't tried it for this recurrence,
我这次没有求
but you should be able to do exactly the same form.
你可以用相同方式求得
Argue that T is greater than or equal to c_1*n^2 - c_2*n.
证明T(n)比c₁·n²-c₂·n大
I didn't check whether that particular form will work,
我没有验证这个形式是否正确
but I think it does.
但我觉得是对的
Try it.
大家自己试下
These other methods will give you,
用别的方法也可以
in some sense, upper and lower bounds
在某种意义上 得到上下界
if you are a little bit careful.
只要更认真一些
But, to really check things,
若要验证正确性
you pretty much have to do the substitution method.
最好还是选择用代换法
And you will get some practice with that.
我们有用这方法的习题
Usually we only care about upper bounds.
一般我们只关心上界
Proving upper bounds like this is what we will focus on,
找到上界是我们所关心的
but occasionally we need lower bounds.
但偶尔也需要下界
It is always nice to know that you have the right answer
提供一个相应的下界
by proving a matching lower bound.
得到正确答案总是好的
The next method we will talk about
我们要讲的下一种方法
is the recursion-tree method.
是递归树法
And it is a particular way of adding up a recurrence,
这是一种解递归式的特别方法
and it is my favorite way.
是我最喜欢的方法
It usually just works. That's the great thing about it.
它总是能用  这是最棒的一点
It provides you intuition for free.
这给你一种直觉
It tells you what the answer is pretty much.
让你大概知道答案是多少
It is slightly nonrigorous,
只是有些不严谨
this is a bit of a pain,
这有点蛋疼
so you have to be really careful when you apply it.
所以用这方法时要特别小心
Otherwise, you might get the wrong answer.
不然  就可能得到错误答案
Because it involves dot, dot, dots,
因为它需要用到点 点 点
our favorite three characters,
我们最喜欢的符号
but dot, dot, dots are always a little bit nonrigorous
但使用省略号总是有一点不严谨
so be careful.
所以要小心
Technically, what you should do is find out
严格来讲  我们应该
what the answer is with recursion-tree method.
用递归树法找到答案
Then prove that it is actually right with the substitution method.
然后用代换法验证之
Usually that is not necessary,
但通常不必要这样
but you should at least have in your mind
不过至少你们应当知道
that that is required rigorously.
递归树法有点不严谨
And probably the first few recurrences you solve,
至少在刚开始解递归的时候
you should do it that way.
你们应当验证
When you really understand the recursion-tree method,
当你完全理解递归树法之后
you can be a little bit more sloppy
你可以省些事
if you are really sure you have the right answer.
如果你确信自己得到了正确解
Let's do an example.
我们来做个练习
We saw recursion trees very briefly last time with mergesort
在讲归并排序时用过一点递归树法
as the intuition why it was n log n.
在介绍为何复杂度是nlgn时
And, if you took an example like the one we just did
像刚才这个例子
with the recursion-tree method, it is dead simple.
要是用递归树法解的话就太大材小用了
Just to make our life harder,
我们来玩个复杂些的
let's do a more complicated recursion.
解个复杂些的递归
Here we imagine we have some algorithm.
假设有某个算法
It starts with a problem size n,
问题的规模为n
it recursively solves a problem of size n/4,
先四等分地递归
it then recursively solves a problem of size n/2,
再二等分地递归
and it does n^2 work on the side with nonrecursive work.
再做一个非递归的n²复杂度的工作
What is that? I mean that is a big less obvious, I would say.
这是什么  我只是想让答案不显而易见
What we are going to do is draw a picture,
我们先画个图
and we are just going to expand out that recursion in tree form
用树的形式展开递归
and then just add everything up.
再把所有东西加起来
We want the general picture,
我们要画个框架图
and the general principle in the recursion-tree method
递归树法的基本原理
is we just draw this as a picture.
就是画成这样一张图
We say well, T_n equals the sum of n^2+T(n/4)+T(n/2).
如题所述  T(n)=n²+T(n/4)+T(n/2)
This is a weird way of writing a sum
这种求和的写法很奇怪
but why not write it that way.
但还是要这么写
This is going to be a tree.
这可以构成树
And it is going to be a tree
构成树的方法是
by recursively expanding each of these two leaves.
递归地展开这两个叶节点
I start by expanding T_n to this,
我先将T(n)展开成这样
then I keep expanding,expanding, expanding everything.
然后继续展开  全部展开
Let's go one more step.
再进行一步
We have this n^2, T(n/4), T(n/2)
我们从n²  T(n/4) T(n/2)开始
If we expand one more time,
再展开一次
this is going to be n^2 plus two things.
得到n²和另两个东西
The first thing is going to be (n/4)^2,
第一个是(n/4)²
the second thing is going to be (n/2)^2.
第二个是(n/2)²
Plus their recursive branches.
以及它们的递归分支
We have T(n/16) and T(n/8).
得到T(n/16)和T(n/8)
Here my arithmetic shows thin.
我算术学得不太好
This better be the same, T(n/8),
这也是T(n/8)
and this should be T(n/4), I believe.
这个是T(n/4)  我觉得
You just keep going forever, I mean,
你可以一直往下写
until you get down to the base case where T is a constant.
直到到达基本情况  T是常数
So, I am now going to skip some steps and say dot, dot, dot.
我略掉下面的步骤 点 点 点
This is where you have to be careful.
这是你们要小心的地方
We have n^2, (n/4)^2, (n/2)^2.
已求得n²  (n/4)²  (n/2)²
Now this is easy because I have already done them all.
我们已经求出这些
(n/16)^2, (n/8)^2, (n/8)^2 again,
(n/16)²  (n/8)²  又是(n/8)²
(n/4)^2 and et cetera, dot, dot, dot,
(n/4)²及其他省略掉的内容 点 点 点
of various levels of recursion here.
递归的不同层次
At the bottom, we are going to get a bunch of constants.
最后  我们会到达一堆常数
These are the leaves.
这些是叶节点
I would like to know how many leaves there are.
我们需要知道这里有多少叶节点
One challenge is how many leaves in this tree could there be?
求叶节点数目是个难题
This is a bit subtle,
这有些难解
unlike mergesort or unlike the previous recurrence we solved,
不像归并排序或我们之前解过的递归
the number of leaves here is a bit funny
叶节点数有点不一样
because we are recursing at different speeds.
因为递归速度不同
This tree is going to be much smaller than this tree.
这棵子树比那棵子树小
It is going to have smaller depth
子树的高度较小
because it has already done down to n/16.
这棵已经减到n/16
Here it has only gone down to n/4.
这棵才减到n/4
But how many leaves are there in this recursion tree?
但这递归树中到底有多少叶节点呢
All I need is an upper bound,
我需要一个上界
some reasonable upper bound.
一个合理的上界
I can tell you it is at most n^10,
我可以说最多是n¹⁰
but that is a bit unreasonable.
但这有些不合理
It should be less than n, good.
它应该小于n  很好
Why is it less than n?
为什么会小于n呢
Exactly. I start with a problem of size n.
很对 最开始的问题大小是n
And I recurse into a problem that n/4 and a problem that says n/2
递归成一个n/4的问题和一个n/2的问题
When I get down to one I stop.
递归到1为止
So, n/4 + n/2 = 3n/4, which is strictly less than n.
n/4+n/2=3n/4  显然比n小
So, definitely the total number
所以  显然
of leaves has to be at most n.
叶节点数不超过n
If I start out with n sort of stuff
若初始规模是n
and get rid of a quarter of it and then recurse,
每次递归减少1/4
it is definitely going to be less than n stuff at the bottom.
递归结束时必然少于n个
So, strictly less than n leaves.
严格小于n个叶节点
At this point, I have done nothing interesting.
到这一点  一切都还很乏味
And then the second cool idea in recursion trees
递归树的第二个亮点是
is you don't just expand this tree and see what it looks like
你不必要展开看整个树的样子
and then say, well, God, how the hell am I going to sum that?
然后说  天啊  这玩意怎么求和
You sum it level by level.
你一层一层地求和
That is the only other idea.
这是第二个思想
It usually works really, really well.
这通常很正确
Here it is a bit complicated
这里有一点复杂
and I have to think a bit to figure out n^2 is n^2.
我们算出的n²就是n²
That is the first level. Easy.
这是第一层  很简单
The second level, I have to think a lot harder.
第二层相对难一些
There are three kinds of mathematicians,
搞数学的人有三种
those who can add and those who cannot,
会计算的和不会的
and I am the latter kind so I need your help.
我是后一种  所以需要你们帮助
Can you add these things together?
你们会把这些加起来吗
It's n^2 over something.
得到n²除以什么
Please? 5/16. Good, thanks.
什么  5/16  好  谢谢
Now I really need your help.
现在真的需要你们帮助了
I think that one I could have done,
上一个我还会做
but this one is a little bit harder.
这个更难了
I will go look at my notes while you compute that.
你们先算着  我去看一下讲稿
Any answers? 73/256.
有答案了吗  73/256
Anyone else confirm that?
有人确认一下吗
It seems a bit high to me.
这个有点大了
73 does not sound right to me. I can cheat.
73听上去不太对 因为我有答案
64? Closer.
64吗  比较接近了
It is actually important that we get this right.
我们必须把这个算对
The 256 is correct.
256这个数是对的
I can tell. Everyone should know that 16^2= 256.
我也知道  谁都知道16²=256
We are computer scientists.
毕竟我们是搞计算机的
25, good. We have two people saying 25,
25  好的  有两个人算得25
therefore it is correct by democracy.
民主地讲 这就是答案
25 is also what my notes say, and I computed it at home.
我的讲稿上也是25  我在家算的
25 is the right answer.
25这个数是对的
Now, did anyone notice something magical about this progression?
有人看出其中的玄妙了吗
It squares each time, good.
它每次都会平方  很好
And, if we were going to add these up, you might call it?
要想把这数列加起来  我们称之为什么
A geometric series, very good.
几何级数[等比级数]  非常好
So, it turns out this is geometric.
原来它是个几何级数
And we know how to sum geometric series,
我们会几何级数的求和
at least you should.
至少你们应该会
We started n^2.
我们从n²开始
We know that at the bottom,
显然在最后的地方
well, this is not quite a level, we get something like n,
高度不是一样的  对于n
but we are decreasing geometrically.
它以几何级数递减
So, the total, I mean the solution to the recurrence
最终  我是说这个递归的解
is the sum of all the numbers in this tree.
就是把这个树里的所有数加起来
If we added it up level by level and then add up all the levels
我们一层一层地加  再把所有层加起来
that is going to give us the answer.
就能得到最终答案
This is the total computed level by level.
一层一层地加出总和
It is just a cute way to compute it.
这是个很聪明的计算方法
It usually gives you nice answers like geometric answers.
通常会得到类似几何级数的结果
We have n^2(1+5/16+...)
这里有  n²(1+5/16+...)
And, if we believe in fate and we see this three number recurrence
如果相信命运的话  看到前3个数
we know that we have the right answer.
我们就知道结果肯定是对的
In general, it is going to be (5^k)/(16^k),
通项是5 /16
at least we hope, and so on.
至少希望是这样
And it keeps going.
k不断变大
It doesn't go on infinitely,
但它不是无穷的
but let's just assume it goes on infinitely.
但可以假设它是无穷的
That will be an upper bound that goes on forever.
这样它就是上界
This is all times n^2.
这些都要乘以n²
Now,if you are going to know one thing about geometric series,
几何级数有一个性质
you should know that 1 + 1/2+ 1/4. If you sum all the powers of 2
大家应该知道 1+1/2+1/4+...  加起来
you get 2.
结果是2
We are computer scientists.
作为计算机科学家
We have got to know at least the binary case.
我们至少得知道二进制的例子
This is like writing 0.1111111 in binary,
这就是在二进制里的0.1111111
actually  1.1111111
准确的说  1.1111111
0.1111 forever is same as 1, so this is 2.
无限的0.1111等于1  所以结果是2
This is even smaller.
这里会更小
We have 5/16, that is less than a half and
因为  5/16小于1/2
then we are squaring each time,
然后等比增长
so this is even less than 2.
所以这里比2还小
If you want, there is a nifty formula
如果你想  有精确的公式
for solving the general geometric series,
你可以对几何级数求和
but all we need is that it is a constant.
但我们只需要它是常数就够了
This is O(n^2). It is also Ω(n^2).
答案是O(n²)  也是Ω(n²)
It is pretty obvious that it is Ω(n^2)
其实很显然它是Ω(n²)
because the top thing is n^2.
因为递归式里就有n²
So, there is our lower bound of n^2.
所以n²也是下界
And we have it within a factor of 2, which is pretty good.
这里的系数是2  很好
You actually get a better factor here.
其实还可以得到一个更好的系数
So, that is recursion-tree method.
这就是递归树方法
It is a little shaky here
不是太严谨
because we have these dot, dot, dots,
因为过程中有省略的地方
and we just believe that it is geometric.
而且 还是等比还是假设出来的
It turns out most of the time it is geometric.
实际中很多时候它都是等比的
No problem here.
这里是没问题的
I would definitely check it with the substitution method
如果是我  我会用代换法检查一遍
because this is not obvious to me
因为我没有明显看出
that it is going to be geometric.
这是一个几何级数
In the cases we will look at in a moment,
在我们马上要看到的例子里
it will be much clearer,
求解会更加清晰
so clear that we can state a theorem
以至于可以得出一个定理
that everything is working fine.
那时一切都好办了
And still time, good.
还有时间  很好
So, that was recursion-trees.
上面讲的是递归树方法
There is one more method we are going to talk about,
接下来我们还要介绍一种方法[主方法]
and you could essentially think of it
你可以认识它本质上是
as an application of the recursion-tree method
递归树方法的一个应用
but it is made more precise.
但是它更精确
And it is an actual theorem, whereas recursion trees,
不同于递归树含有省略  有待证明
if the dot, dot, dots aren't obvious,you better check them.
主方法基于一个定理[主定理]
The sad part about the master method is it is pretty restrictive.
遗憾的是  主方法限制颇多
It only applies to a particular family of recurrences.
只能应用到特定的递归式上
It should be T(n) = aT(n/b) + f(n).
这些递归式符合T(n) = aT(n/b) + f(n)
Am I going to call it f? Yes, I will call it f.
是叫f吗  对的
In particular, it will not cover the recurrence I just solved
因此  它不包含我刚才解的递归式
because I was recursing on two different problems
因为那个递归式有两个不同的子问题
of different sizes.
子问题的规模也不同
Here, every problem you recurse on
在主方法中  每个子问题
should be of the same size.
的规模应该相等
There are a subproblems.
有a个相同的子问题
A way to think of this is a recursive algorithm.
适用于主方法的递归算法
Each of them is of size n/b,
每个子问题的规模都是 n/b
so the total costs will be this.
因此递归的总代价是这个
Then you are doing f(n) nonrecursive work.
剩下的是非递归的代价 f(n)
A few constraints. a should be at least 1,
一些约束条件  a要大于或等于1
should have at least 1 recursion.
至少递归一次
b should be strictly greater than 1.
b要严格大于1
You better make the problem smaller
你得让子问题规模减小
or else it is going to be infinity.
不然结果是无限大
And f(n) should have some nice property.
f(n)函数要满足一些性质
f(n) should be asymptotically positive.
f(n) 渐近趋正
How many people know what asymptotically positive means?
有多少人知道渐近趋正是什么意思
No one. OK, you haven't read the textbook. That's OK.
没人  看来你们没看教材
I haven't read it either, although don't tell Charles.
我也没看  可别告诉Charles
And he'd notice.
不过他会发现的
And what might you think asymptotically positive means?
你觉得渐近趋正是什么意思
That we can do a little bit better.
这样会好点
Sorry?
能再说一遍吗
Yes, it means for large enough n, f(n) is positive.
它表示对足够大的n  f(n)是正的
This means f(n) is greater than zero for n, at least some n_o,
存在某特定n₀ 当n≥n₀时  f(n)大于0
so for some constant n_o.
对于某个常数n₀
Eventually it should be positive.
f(n)最终是正的
I mean, we don't care about
由此可见  如果当n=1时
whether it's negative 1 for n=1, not a big deal.
f(n)=-1  不用担心  无所谓
It won't affect the answer
不影响结果
because we only care about the asympotics within.
因为我们只考虑渐近的情况
The master method, you gave it a recurrence of this form,
当你得到这种形式的递归式
it tells you the answer.
使用主方法可以得出结果
That is the great thing about the master method.
这是主方法很棒的地方
The annoying thing about the master method
比较烦的是
is that it has three cases.
主方法有三种情况
It is a big long.
内容很多
It takes a little bit longer to memorize than all the others
相对前两种方法  需要更长的时间记忆
because the others are just ideas.
因为之前的都只是思路
Here we need to actually remember a few things.
这里却要记忆一堆东西
Let me state the theorem.
我把定理写出来
Well, not quite yet.
也不尽然
There is one very simple idea,
主方法有个简单的思路
which is we are going to compare this nonrecursive work f(n)
就是去比较  非递归的函数f(n)
with a very particular function n^logb(a).
和  函数n^logba
Why n^logb(a)? You will see later.
为什么是n^logba  等会儿就知道了
It turns out it is the number of leaves in the recursion tree,
它是递归树叶节点的数量
but that is foreshadowing.
埋个伏笔
So, it is either less, equal or bigger.
三种情况分别是小于  等于  大于
And here we care about asymptotics.
我们只考虑渐近情况
And we have to be a little bit more precise
而且还更确切地关注
about less, equal or bigger.
小于 等于 或大于
You might think well, it means little o, big Theta, or little omega.
你可能会想到  小o  大Θ  小ω
It would be nice if the theorem held for all of those cases,
若定理对上述条件都成立  那当然好
but it leaves some gaps.
但是中间存在一些真空地带
Let's start with Case 1.
情况1
Case 1 is when f(n) is smaller.
情况1是f(n)较小的情况
And not just that it is little o,
不只是小o符号
but it is actually quite a bit smaller.
实际上还要更小些
It has got to be polynomially smaller than n^logb(a).
它得多项式地小于n^logba
For some positive epsilon, the running time should be this n
对于正的ε  运行时间是
to this constant log base b of a minus that epsilon,
n^(logba–ε)
so it is really polynomially smaller than n^logb(a).
所以它多项式地小于n^logba
We cannot handle the little o case,
我们不能用小o符号
that's a little bit too strong.
那玩意太强了
This is saying it is really quite a bit smaller.
这里比小o符号要更小
But the answer then is really simple, T(n) = Θ( n^logb(a) ).
但结果很简单  T(n)=Θ(n^logba)
Great. That is Case 1.
好的  这就是情况1
Case 2 is when f(n) is pretty much equal to n^logb(a).
情况2  当f(n)基本上等于n^logba
And by pretty much equal I mean
基本等于的意思是
up to poly log factors.
在把lg多项式作为因式的基础上
This is log base 2 of n to the power k.
这是以2为底n的对数的k次幂
You should know this notation.
你应该知道这个符号
For example,k could be zero.
比如  k可以是0
And then they are equal up to constant factors,
所以它就是常数了
for some k greater than or equal to zero.
这里k必须要大于或等于0
Less than will not work,
小于0不行
so it is really important that k is non-negative.
所以k是非负的
It should probably be an integer.
它可能应该是一个整数
It doesn't actually matter whether there is an integer,
不  是不是整数无所谓
but there it is. It could n^logb(a) times lg n
在这里  可以是n^logba乘以lgn
or just times nothing, whatever.
或者  乘以1
Again, the solution is easy here,
同样  结果很简单
T = Θ( n^logb(a)…).
T(n)=Θ(n^logba…)
Presumably it has to be at least times lg^k.
大概至少是  乘以lg^k
It turns out it is lg to the k plus 1 of n.
实际是  (lgn)^(k+1)
That is Case 2.
这是情况2
We have one more case which is slightly more complicated.
剩下的情况3稍微复杂一点
We need to assume slightly more for Case 3.
需要做更多的假设
But Case 3 is roughly
情况3粗略的讲是
when f(n) grows bigger than n^logb(a).
f(n)比n^logba增长的快
So, it should be capital Omega,
所以是  大Ω符号
here is one place where we get to use omega,
这就是用Ω的地方
n^logb(a) for some positive epsilon.
n^logba  加上正的ε
It should grow not just bigger but polynomially bigger.
f(n)不仅要大于  且要多项式地大于
Here it was growing just a log factor bigger, poly log,
情况2是大一个lg多项式因式
and here it is a polynomial factor.
情况3则是大一个多项式因式
In this case,we need another assumption about f(n)
同时  还对f(n)有要一个假设
because we worry a little bit about how quickly f(n) grows.
因为我们考虑f(n)如何增长
We want to make sure
我们要确保
that as you go down the recursion f gets smaller.
在递归的过程中  f不断变小
It would be kind of nice if f gets smaller as you go down,
在递归中f不断变小就好
otherwise you are, again,
不然
trying to sum to infinity or whatever.
在相加后  得到无限大就麻烦了
I see why this is for some epsilon prime greater than zero.
这里应该写ε' 存在ε'大于0
What I would like is that if I just sort of take the recurrence,
我想要这种效果  对于递归式
this T(n) and just throw in fs instead,
把T(n)全部替换成f(n)
f(n) should be somehow related to af(n/b).
f(n)一定要和af(n/b)有这种关系
What I would like is that
我希望这样
f(n), which is at the top of the recursion tree,
f(n)即递归树的最高层
should be bigger than the thing at the next level down.
应该大于下一层
The sum of all the values at the next level down
大于下一层所有值之和
should be bigger by some constant factor.
需要大某个常数因子
Here I have the next level down is at most some 1 - ε,
在这里  下一层至多等于(1-ε)f
something strictly less than 1,
(1-ε)严格小于1
some constant strictly less than 1
这个系数要严格小于1
times the thing at the top level.
至多是这个系数乘以上一层
I need that to make sure things are getting smaller as I go down.
我需要此条件保证每层的数量越来越小
Then T(n) = Θ(f(n)).
结果  T(n)=Θ(f(n))
And that is the theorem.
这就是定理
This is the master theorem or whatever you want to call it.
你可以叫它主定理
It is not named after some guy name Master.
不是以某个人名来命名的
It is just the master of all methods
而是因为它是最主要的方法
because it is very easy to apply.
应用起来很方便
Let's apply it a few times.
我们来练习几个
It is a bit much to take in all at once.
一次练习完可能有点多
And then I will give you a sketch of the proof
练习之后我简略的证明一下主定理
to see that it is really not that surprising this is true
如果你看了它的递归树的话
if you look at the recursion-tree.
会发现 它的正确性显而易见
But first let's just try using it.
但首先  我们先用一用它
For example, we could take T(n) = 4T(n/2) +n.
比如  T(n)=4T(n/2)+n
This is a, this is b,this is f(n).
这是a  这是b  这是f(n)
The first thing we should compute is n^logb(a).
先计算一下n^logba
This I think even I can do.
连我都会算
Log base 2 of 4. Yeah, log base 2 I can do.
底数为2的4的对数  我算算
This is n^2.
就是n²
OK, so is f(n) smaller or bigger than n^2?
f(n)比n²大还是小
Well, f(n) = n.
f(n)=n
n^2 is clearly bigger by a polynomial factor.
n²当然比n 大一个多项式因式
So, we are in Case 1.
所以是情况1
What is the answer?
答案是什么
n^2, yeah.
n的平方  对
It is theta n^log_ba, which here it is just n^2.
这是Θ(n^logba)  这就刚好是 n²
Let's do some slight variation.
我们稍微改一下题目
I am going to keep a and b the same and just change f.
我将保持a和b不变  只改变f的值
Let's say T(n)=4T(n/2)+n^2.
T(n)=4T(n/2)+n²
This is like drill spelling.
这有点像是拼字练习
n^2 is asymptotically the same as n^2 even up to constants.
n²渐近地等于n² 相差只有一些常数
What is the answer? This is Case 2.
答案是什么呢  这是情况2
It is slightly harder.
这个稍微有点难
What is k in this example? Zero.
这个例子里k等于多少?  零
The answer is? Survey says?
所以答案是什么? 调查结果表明?
N^2 log n.
n²lgn
Good. And a couple more.
好  再来几个
T(n)=4T(n/2) + n^3. What is the answer?
T(n)=4T(n/2)+n³  结果是什么
n^3.
n的立方
This is Case 3.
这是情况3
I know this is pretty boring.
我知道这挺无聊的
At this point we are just applying this stupid theorem.
这种情况下我们正好使用这个愚蠢的定理
How about n^2/lg n?
n²/lgn的结果是什么
What is the answer?
答案是什么?
Good. In this case no one should answer.
好  这种情况下没人回答
It is a big tricky. I forget exactly the answer.
很棘手的问题  我恰好忘了答案
I think it is like n^2 log log n over log n,no?
我想这就类似于 n²lglgn/lgn吗
Oh, no. n^2 log log n, that's right.Yeah.
哦  不  n²lglgn  好
But you shouldn't know that,
但是你不应该知道那些
and this doesn't follow from the master method.
这不是从主方法中得出的
This is something you would have to solve,
你们得自己解了
probably with the recursion-tree
或许通过递归树可以
would be a good way to do this one,
是解的好办法
and you need to know some properties of logs
你得知道一些对数的性质
to know how that goes.
知道它的运算方法
But here the master method does not apply.
但是这里主方法并不适用
And so you have to use a different method.
所以你还是要使用其他的方法
OK. The last thing I want to do is
好  最后我想
tell you why the master method is true,
告诉你们为什么主方法是正确的
and that makes it much more intuitive,
那会让它更有直观
especially using recursion-trees,
我要用递归树证明
why everything works.
它为什么成立
This is a sketch of a proof, not the full thing.
这只是证明的一个梗概  还不是全部的
You should read the proof in the textbook.
详细的证明大家可以看书
It is not that much harder than what I will show,
倒不是说书上比我这里证明得容易
but it is good for you to know the formal details.
但是了解正式证明中的细节对你们有好处
I don't have time here to do all of the details.
这里我没有时间给大家演示所有的细节
I will just tell you the salient parts.
我只能告诉大家重要的部分
This is the proof sketch or the intuition
这是证明的梗概 或者说思路
behind the master method.
关于主方法的由来
What we are going to do is just take the recursion-tree
我们接下来要做的只是运用递归树法
for this recurrence
来解递归
and add up each level and then add up all the levels
然后将每一层加起来 再层层相加
and see what we get.
再看看我们得出什么
We start with f at the top after we have expanded one level.
从最顶端的f开始展开第一层
Then we get a different problems, each of size n/b.
展开为a个规模为n/b的问题
And after we expand them it will f for each one.
在我展开它们之后  每一个都是f(n/b)
They are all the same size.
它们规模相同
Then we expand all of those and so on,
然后我们能继续展开所有的f(n/b)
and we get another a subproblems from there.
然后我们能从这里得到其他的子问题
We are going to get like f.
我们将得到 f(n/b²)
That is sort of decreasing geometrically the size,
规模呈几何级数递减
and so on and so on and so on,
等等  等等
until at the bottom we get constant size problems.
直到我们在底部得出常数规模的问题
This is a bit special because this is the base case,
这有点特殊  因为这是基本情况
but we have some other constant at the bottom.
我们在底部得到别的常量
We would like to know how many leaves there are,
我们想知道有多少叶节点
but that is a little bit tricky at the moment.
但是这时候稍微有些棘手
Let's first compute the height of this tree.
我们首先计算树的高度
Let me draw it over here.
我在这边画出来
What is the height of this tree?
树的高度是多少
I start with a problem of size n.
我从问题n开始
I want to get down to a problem of size 1.
我想一直向下直到问题规模为1
How long does that take?
高度是多少
How many levels?
有多少层
This is probably too easy for some
对于部分同学可能很简单
and not at your fingertips for others.
但对于其他同学还不是触手可及
Log base b of n, good.
logbn  好
The height of this tree is n^log_b,
树的高度是 logbn
because it is just how many times
因为这正是一直除以b
I divide by b until I get down to 1.
直到降到1 所需要的次数
That is great.
好极了
Now I should be able to compute the number of leaves
现在应该就可以计算叶节点的数量了
because I have branching factor a,
因为我有一个分支因子 a
I have height h.
还有高度 h
The number of leaves is a^h, a^log_bn.
所以叶节点的数量是 a^h a^logbn
Let me expand that a little bit.
我展开来写
a^log_bn, properties of logs,
a^logbn  跟对数的性质
we can take the n downstairs and put the a upstairs,
我们能把n放在下边  把a放在上边
and we get n^log_ba. Our good friend n^log_ba.
我们就得到了logba  老朋友 logba
So, that is why our good friend n^log_ba is
所以  这就是logba
so important in the master method.
在主方法中这么重要的原因
What we are doing is comparing f,
我们要做的是比较
which is the top level,
在最顶层的f
to n^log_ba, which up to theta is the bottom level.
和最底层的 logba
Now the leaves are all at the same level
现在所有的叶节点在同一层
because we are decreasing at the same rate in every branch.
因为每一个分支上都以同样的速度递减
If I add up the cost at the bottom level,
将底层的代价加起来
it is Theta n^log_ba.
得到 Θ(logba)
I add up the things at the top level
把顶层的加起来
it is f(n), not terribly exciting.
得到是f(n)  有点无聊
But the next level,
但是在下一级
this is a little bit more interesting, is af(n/b),
这就有点意思  是af(n/b)
which should look familiar
看起来很熟悉吧
if you had the master method already memorized, it is that.
如果你已经熟记了主方法  这个就是
So, we know that af(n/b) has decreased by some constant factor,
我们知道 af(n/b) 已经减少了某常量倍
1-epsilon prime.
1-ε'
We have gone down.
计算到这
This is a constant factor smaller than this.
这个比这个小某常数倍
And then you sum up the next level.
然后对下一层求和
It is going to be like a^2f(n/b^2).
会得出a²f(n/b²)这样的结果
I see that I actually wrote this wrong, the parentheses.
我看到我把这个写错了  括号里的内容
Sorry about that.
对不起
It is not (n/b)^2. It is n/b^2.
不是(n/b)²  而是n/b²
So, this sequence, in Case 3 at least,
所以这个数列  至少在情况3中
is decreasing geometrically.
是呈几何级数递减的
If it is decreasing geometrically up to constant factors,
如果它以几何级数递减
it is dominated by the biggest term, which is f(n).
最大项f(n)就会占据主导
Therefore, in Case 3, we get Theta(f(n)).
因此  在情况3中  我们得到 Θ(f(n))
Let's look at the other cases,
我们看看其他的情况
and let me adapt those cases to how much time we have left.
根据剩下的时间的情况 看讲多少
Wow, lot's of time.
太多时间了
Five minutes. Tons of time.
五分钟  太多时间了
What to do? Let me write that down.
做些什么  我把它写下来
Case 3, the costs decrease.
情况3  代价逐渐降低
Now, this is a place I would argue
这里我需要说明
where the dot, dot, dot is pretty obvious.
这里的省略是很显然的
Here, this is damn simple, it is a^kf.
这些无比简单的  (a^k)f(n/b^k)
And, in Case 3, we assume that the costs decrease geometrically
情况3中  我们假设成本呈几何级数降低
as we go down the tree.
顺着树向下
That was sort of backwards to start with Case 3.
从情况3开始往回讨论
Let's do Case 1,
让我们来看看情况1
which is sort of the other intuitively easy case.
这是一种直观的简单情况
In Case 1, we know that f is polynomially smaller than this thing.
在情况1中  我们知道f(n) 多项式地小于这个
And we are sort of changing
我们可以说是
by this very simple procedure in the middle.
从中间改变了这个的顺序
I am going to wave my hands if this is
如果大家想要正式的证明
where you need a more formal argument.
我是不会做的
I claim that this will increase geometrically.
我敢说这将会呈几何级数增长
It has to increase geometrically because this f
它必须呈几何级数增长  因为这f(n)
is polynomially smaller than this one,
多项式地 比这个小
you are going to get various polynomials in the middle
你将在中间得到很多种多项式
which interpret geometrically from the small one to the big one.
必然需要从小到大 呈几何级数上升
Therefore, the big one dominates because it is, again,
因此  大的占主导地位  但它还是
geometric series.
几何级数
As I said, this is intuition, not a formal argument.
正如我所说  这是直觉  不能算正式的证明
This one was pretty formal because we assumed it,
上面这个证明就很正式了  因为我们进行了假设
but here you need a bit more argument.
但是这里我们需要更多地论证
They may not increase geometrically
它们不一定非要呈几何级数增长
but they could increase faster,
它们也许会增长的更快
and that is also fine.
这也有可能
So, in Case 3, you are dominated,
所以  在情况3中  占主导的
I mean you are always dominated
我是说 占主导的总是
by the biggest term in a geometric series.
几何级数中的最大项
Here it happens to be f
情况3中是f(n)
and here you are dominated by n^log_ba
而这里  占主导的是logba
with a bottom term, oh, Theta.
底层那个  写上Θ
Case 2,
情况2
here it is pretty easy
这里这个非常简单
but you need to know some properties of logs.
但是你需要知道一些对数的性质
In Case 2,
在情况2中
we assume that all of these are basically the same.
我们假设所有的这些是基本相同的
I mean, we assume that the top is equal to the bottom.
我是说  我们假设顶层与底层相等
And this is changing in this very procedural way.
由于中间的过程很有规律
Therefore, all of the ones in the middle
因此  所有的中间的这些
have to be pretty much the same.
必须基本一致
Not quite because here we don't have the log factor.
不完全一致  因为这里没有lg因式
Here we have a log to the k.
而这里有一个lg的k次方
We have n^log_ba times log to the kn.
logba乘以(lg^k)n
Here we don't have the log to the k.
这里则没有lg的k次方
So, the logs do disappear here.
lg在过程中没有了
It turns out the way they disappear is pretty slowly.
消失的方式是很缓慢的
If you look at the top half of these terms,
如果你观察这上半部分
they will all have log to the k.
它们都含有lg的k次方
The bottom half they will start to disappear.
在下半部分它们将开始消失
I am giving you some oracle information.
我给你们一些令人来自神灵的信息
If you take logs and you don't change the argument by too much,
如果你算对数  你不把参数改变得太厉害
the logs remain.
对数值不变
Maybe halfway is too far.
也许半路有点太远
The claim is that each level is roughly the same,
要求是每一级都大致相同
especially the upper most levels are all asymptotically equal.
特别是上面的大部分层都渐进地相等
Roughly the same.
大致相同
And, therefore, the cost is one level,
因此  总代价是其中一层
here like f times the number of levels, h.
比如f乘以树的高度h
And h is log base b of n.
h也就是logbn
B is a constant so we don't care.
b是一个常量我们不用在意
This is Theta(lgn).
因此得到Θ(lgn)
And, therefore,we get T = n^log_ba lg^kn times another log n.
因此  我们得到T(n)=logba·(lg^k)n乘以另一个lgn
So, we get f(n) times log n.
所以我们得出f(n)·lgn
That is the very quick sketch.
那是非常粗略的证明
Sorry, I am being pretty fuzzy on Cases 1 and 2.
抱歉  情况1和2都讲得太模糊了
Read the proof because you will have to,
记得回去看证明  你们必须看
at some point, manipulate logs in that way.
某些时刻  需要那样处理对数
And that is all. Any questions?
就到这里  有什么问题吗?
Or, you are all eager to go. OK.
你们都渴望下课了  好吧
Thanks. See you Wednesday.
谢谢  周三见